Guide to the Mae and Harry Millstone Papers WAG.303
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mae and Harry Millstone Papers
1910-2009
1960-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Millstone, David H.
Millstone, Mae Kaplan
Millstone, Harry
WAG.303
11 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 cassette storage box, and 3 oversize flat boxes.
3 videocassettes (vhs)
5 audiocassettes
14.4 Gigabytes in 4 computer files.
Mae Kaplan Millstone (1913-2009) was a newspaper section editor, union organizer, and activist for the labor movement and women's issues. Harry Millstone (1907-1999) was a union organizer, instructor, and activist for the labor movement. Mae and Harry met in Detroit while organizing with the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), and married in 1938. The Mae and Harry Millstone Papers contain material documenting their work and support for labor unions and the labor movement, both separately and together. Of note in this collection is a digital recording of the 2005 video interviews with Mae describing her life-long work and support for the labor movement, as well as her activism, dating from the 1930s to the 2000s. This collection also contains appointment books, as well as print material, training course manuals, and newsletters related to labor organizing. A scrapbook from the 1960s and subject files pertaining to women's issues document Mae's editorial work for the women's section of The Gazette and Daily in York, Pennsylvania. Family papers include travel diaries, ephemera, correspondence, and audio recordings and lyric sheets for labor movement-related songs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by David Millstone, 2009. The accession number associated with this gift is 2009.077.
Appraisal
The following audio and video carriers with commercial recordings were separated from the collection: "Tom Juravich--Rising Again"; "Michael Parenti-the US War on Yugoslavia"; "Noam Chomsky - Kosovo and Iraq"; "US Holocaust Memorial Museum: Witnesses to the Holocaust";"Uprising of 1934"; and "1983 pay equity."
Arrangement
Organized chronologically within three series:
Series I. Mae Kaplan Millstone
Series II. Harry Millstone
Series III. Family
Biographical Note
Mae Kaplan Millstone (1913-2009) graduated with a Master's degree in Sociology from Pennsylvania State University in 1934, and worked during the mid-1930s for the National Industrial Recovery Administration as a Special Investigator through the Pennsylvania Department of Labor and Industry. She moved to Detroit in 1936 where she met Harry Millstone (1907-1999), who was a unionizer for the CIO at the time. They married in 1938. In 1941 they moved to Williamsport, Pennsylvania and Mae left the workforce to raise their two children, but continued to volunteer in consumer and voter registration activities. The family moved to York, Pennsylvania in 1961, where Mae became the editor of the women's section for The Gazette and Daily newspaper. She also stayed active in her community by co-founding the group York Action for Peace, and continued her support of the labor movement. She was also active in the York Chapter of the National Organization for Women (NOW) and volunteered for Planned Parenthood. Harry was employed by Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America for many years as a union organizer and retired in 1973. He continued to educate others, teaching various courses on union organizing at the George Meany Center for Labor Studies during the 1980s. In 1999 he received the Pillar of Labor from the Tamiment Library and Wagner Labor Archives.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
A majority of the audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives [special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Mae and Harry Millstone Papers (dated 1910-2009) consist of materials created and collected by Mae and Harry Millstone over the course of their lives as they worked and advocated for labor unions and workers' rights. This collection also includes files related to specific jobs held by Mae and Harry, as well as material representing them as a family and their combined interests. Files in this collection document Mae's work in the 1930s as a government investigator of the working conditions of women and children workers, as well as her involvement with the U.S. Office of Price Administration Labor Advisory Committee during World War II. This collection also includes material accumulated by Harry during his time with the Army Service Forces for the Quartermaster at Camp Lee in the 1940s. Mae's later work in the 1960s and 1970s as a women's section editor for the York, Pennsylvania The Gazette and Daily is documented in a scrapbook and subject files. Of particular note in this collection are the digital recordings of Mae's video interviews with her son, in which she describes her work and activism thoughout her life. This collection also contains Mae's appointment books with daily entries dating from the late 1950s to the 2000s. Harry's work with Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America and other organizations is well documented in this collection through his promotional print material and ephemera. Harry's instructor course manuals for his classes on union organizing are also in this collection dating from the 1980s. The family material includes trip diaries, correspondence, and ephemera, as well as audio recordings and print lyrics of labor movement and peace movement-related songs.
Labor movement -- United States -- 20th century.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Fliers (printed matter); Clippings (information artifacts); Appointment books.; Women's rights -- United States -- 20th century; Peace movements -- United States.; Millstone, David H.; Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America; AFL-CIO. Department of Organization and Field Services; Pennsylvania. Bureau of Women and Children
- Series I. Mae Kaplan Millstone, 1920s-2009; 7.50 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes and 2 oversize flat boxes.; 14.4 Gigabytes in 4 computer files.; 1 audiocassette; 3 videocassettes (vhs)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material related to the work and activism of Mae Kaplan Millstone. Early files include a small amount of school papers from the 1920s and 1930s. Reports, charts, and notes in this series document her work in the mid-1930s as an investigator for the Pennsylvania Department of Labor and Industry Bureau of Women and Children regarding work environments and compliance. Mae's engagement calendars include daily entries of her life and work dating from 1959 to 2005. This series also includes Russian and Chinese language class papers, exercises, and audio recordings. Mae's scrapbook in this series contains women's sections of the York, Pennsylvania The Gazette and Daily from 1962, which was early in her tenure as editor. The subject files in this series were accumulated by Mae during the 1970s, either for use as part of her editing work or as personal reference files. These files reflect issues Mae perceived as affecting and impacting women, including affirmative action, contraception, the Equal Rights Amendement (ERA), feminism, health, religion, sports, and gender descrimination in the workplace. Her files include material on issues that not only affected her directly, but also affected women of color, and women living and working in countries outside the United States including China, Central America, South America, and Japan. These files typically contain press clippings, booklets, and brochures, and include a 1971 copy of Our Bodies, Ourselves. Mae's involvement in the national and York Pennsylvania Chapter of the National Organization for Women (NOW) is illustrated through her collection of organizational publications, photographs, event notices, and print material dating from the 1970s to 1980s. An event program and planning notes for a 1998 banquet in her honor hosted by the York Chapter of NOW is also in this series. Other honors and awards include a 1947 War Service Award for her work serving on the U.S. Office of Price Administration Labor Advisory Committee; and a parade program for her role as Grand Marshall for the 2005 York Labor Day Parade. Of particular note in this series is a digital recording of a 6.5 hour long 2005 video interview conducted by her son, David Millstone, in which Mae reflects on her personal life, work, and life-long activism in support of women's issues, world peace, and the labor movement.
  - Early School Class Papers, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Labor and Industry Bureau of Women and Children – Home-Work Compliance Investigations with Charts, Notes, Reports, Correspondence, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Job Searches -- Correspondence, References, 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications -- International Press Correspondence, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Publications -- IPA News Bulletin, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publications -- In Fact, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Publications -- The Minority of One, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications -- I. F. Stone's Bi-Weekly, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications -- Pennsylvania Commission for Women News, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications -- Womenews and New Directions for Women, 1977-1980 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Publications -- The Defense Monitor, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1945, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - War Service Award, Photograph, and Letter -- for Serving on the U.S. Office of Price Administration Labor Advisory Committee, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Booklet -- The Everyday Tensions in a Woman's Life, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Russian Language Classes -- Exercises and Quizzes, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1959, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1967, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1971-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1985-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Engagement Calendars, 2001-2005 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - York Action for Peace -- Statement of Purpose, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook with Women's Sections from the York, Pennsylvania The Gazette and Daily, 1962 (Box 19)
  - Subject Files -- [Affirmative Action / Legal Aspects], 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files -- [Bibliographies] Re: Working Women, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Subject Files -- [Black Feminists], 1971-1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subject Files -- [Central / South American] Women's Issues, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subject Files -- [China] Women's Issues, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subject Files -- [Contraception / Abortion], 1968-1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subject Files -- [Court Decisions] Re: Working Women and Discrimination, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Subject Files -- [Courtship, Marriage, and Family], 1973-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Subject Files -- [Declining Birth Rate], 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subject Files -- [Education - Athletics], 1973, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Subject Files -- [Equal Employment Opportunity Commission Guidelines on Discrimination Because of Sex], 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Subject Files -- [Equal Rights Amendment (ERA)], 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Subject Files -- [Equal Rights Struggles], 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Subject Files -- [Famous Women], 1971-1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Subject Files -- [Federal Status] -- Equal Employment, 1964-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files -- [Feminism], 1972-1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files -- [He and She], 1971-1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subject Files -- [Health Problems], 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subject Files -- Department of [Health, Education, Welfare (H.E.W.) Guidelines / Rulings], 1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subject Files -- [Homemaking], 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Subject Files -- [Homosexuality], 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Subject Files -- [Income], 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Subject Files -- [Industrialized Countries] -- Women Working, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subject Files -- [International -- United Nations Women's Year, Other], 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Subject Files -- [International] -- Women's Issues, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Subject Files -- [Japan, Korea] -- Women's Issues, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subject Files -- [Labor Department] -- Working Women, 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subject Files -- [Labor Struggle] -- Women, 1968-1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files -- [Mental Health / Alcoholism], 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files -- [Motherhood], 1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Subject Files -- [Organizations] -- Women's, 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subject Files -- [Paid Employment] -- Women, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Subject Files -- [Psychology -- Consciousness Raising], 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Subject Files -- [Publications] -- Women's Issues, 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subject Files -- [Role of Women], 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subject Files -- [Sex Stereotyping], 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subject Files -- Sexual [Discrimination], 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subject Files -- [Sexuality], 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subject Files -- [Socialist / People's Democracies], 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subject Files -- [Sociology -- Changing Lifestyles], 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Subject Files -- [Sex Stereotyping in Schools], 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Subject Files -- [Third World Undeveloped Countries], 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Subject Files -- [Violence Against Women, Abused Wife, Rape], 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Subject Files -- [Women and Crime], 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Subject Files -- [Women and Religion], 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subject Files -- [Women in Literature], 1973-1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Subject Files -- [Women in Politics], 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subject Files -- [Women in Sports], 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files -- [Women in in the Arts], 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files -- [Women's Studies], 1973-1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chinese Language Classes -- Written Lesson Exercises, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chinese Language Classes -- Verbal Lesson and Mae Practice, 1972 (Box 17, Audiocassette 303.0007)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) -- York Chapter / Women's Action York (WAY) -- Clippings, Event Poster, Promotional Material, Photograph, Publications, and Program and Notes for Banquet Honoring Mae, 1972-1978, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 8, Box 18, Folder 3)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) -- Pennsylvania -- Promotional Material, Publications, 1973-1977, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) --National -- Promotional Material, Press Releases, Publications, 1975-1979 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Bibliographic Notes and Research on Women in Labor, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Mae Letter Addressed to Senators Regarding Abortion Rights, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Appreciation -- AFL-CIO Community Services, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Grand Marshall of the York Labor Day Parade -- Mae Program and Photograph, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Mae Oral History Interview Conducted by Son David Millstone -- Video Recording, 2005; cuid36459 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_303_ER_1)
  - Mae Oral History Interview Conducted by Son David Millstone -- Descriptions of Interview Topics for Each DVD, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Mae Oral History Interview Conducted by Son David Millstone -- VHS Copies, 2005 (Box 17, Vhs 303.0001 -- 303.0003)
  - Memorial Program and Obituary -- Mae, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Mae, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Draft of Article on Women in Thailand, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera -- Bumper stickers, Postcards, Print Items for Various World Peace and Labor Organizations, undated (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
- Series II. Harry Millstone, 1942-1987; 4.17 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box.
  This series contains material accumulated by Harry during his service in World War II and his career as a labor organizer and instructor. His early files date from the mid-1940s, and document his time serving in the Army Service Forces at Camp Lee. These files include camp fact sheets, orientation newsletters, training manuals, and bulletins. Harry also wrote articles and presentations related to labor unions and organizing in the late 1950s-early 1960s including an analysis of the Playtex organizing drive and a radio script of a panel discussion he hosted for Wise Potato Chips. A large portion of this series is union organizing-focused fliers, bulletins, and handouts from the 1960s and early 1970s that were distributed by Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America. Some of this print material focused on specific organizing committees for companies including Heinz, Playtex, and Ore-Ida. A plaque for his 1973 retirement and cufflinks and tie clip from Amalgamated are also in this series. Harry also taught instructional courses in the 1980s at the George Meany Center for Labor Studies, and this series contains course manuals for topics including white collar organizing, collective bargaining, and advanced organizing techniques.
  - Army Service Forces at Camp Lee -- Training Packets, Fact Sheets, Booklets, 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
  - U.S. Department of Labor -- Labor Management Brochures and Booklets, 1959-1963 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Writings and Speeches -- Automation Speech -- Support Documents, Research, Script, and Related, 1959-1965 (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
  - Writings and Speeches -- A Report on the Virginia Watermen of the Chesapeake Bay, 1967-08-08 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Writings and Speeches -- Articles on Mexico Industry, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Writings and Speeches -- Unknown Typescript of Fiction Story About Factory Worker in Macon, Missouri, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Writings and Speeches -- "The Playtex Organizing Drive, An Analysis", undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Writings and Speeches -- Wise Potato Chip Radio Interview -- Script with Harry Interview, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Amalgamated -- Food Employees Union -- Print Material, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Amalgamated -- General Print Material, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Amalgamated -- Draper Worker Organizing Committee -- Print Material, 1962, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Amalgamated -- Leas and McVitty Employee Organizing Committee -- Print Material, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Amalgamated -- Ore-Ida Workers Organizing Committee -- Print Material, Radio Script, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Amalgamated -- Allied Kid Workers Organizing Committee -- Print Material, 1966, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Amalgamated -- Letter and Agreement with General Organizers Association, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Amalgamated -- Dakota City IBP Workers Organizing Committee -- Print Material, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Amalgamated -- Playtex Workers Organizing Committee -- Print Material, Notes, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Amalgamated -- Heinz Office and Technical Organizing Committee -- Print Material, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Amalgamated -- Plaques -- "Creed of the Butcher Workman" and Harry's Retirement Proclamation, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
  - Amalgamated -- Pair of Cufflinks and Tie Clip, undated (Box 21)
  - AFL-CIO Department of Organization -- Handbills and Leaflets, 1960s, undated (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
  - AFL-CIO Department of Organization -- Quality Circles: An Organizing Manual, circa 1982 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - United Steel Workers of America and Staffman's Organizing Committee -- Agreement, Letters, Print Material, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Service Employees International Union (SEIU) AFL-CIO -- Organizing Leaflets, Convention Organizing Report, New Member Kits, 1971-1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 2-5)
  - Educational Programs -- Organizing and the Law, Part II -- Course Manual, Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Educational Programs -- Planning Calendar, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Educational Programs -- ACTWU Organizing Institute -- Course Manual, 1978-12-03-1978-12-08 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Educational Programs -- Support Material on Biltmore Plaza Union Organizing Committee for Unknown Course, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Educational Programs -- Collective Bargaining: Negotiating Techniques -- Course Manual, 1979-01-28-1979-02-02 (Box 11, Folder 10, Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Educational Programs -- Advanced Organizing -- Course Manual and Instructional Slides, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Educational Programs -- Understanding the Building Trades -- Learning Guide, August 1981 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Educational Programs -- White Collar Organizing -- Course Guide, 1982-11-07-1982-11-12 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Educational Programs -- Organizing II -- Course Guide, 1983-10-02-1983-10-07 (Box 12, Folder 6, Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Educational Programs -- Advanced Organizing Techniques -- Course Guide, 1984-03-05-1984-03-15 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Educational Programs -- International Chemical Workers Organizing Seminar -- Course Guide, 1984-02-21-1984-02-24 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Educational Programs -- International Chemical Workers Organizing Seminar -- Course Guide, 1987-04-20-1987-04-24 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
  - Educational Programs -- Graphic Communications International Union Leadership Seminar -- Course Guide, 1985-03-24-1985-03-29 (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
  - Educational Programs -- George Meany Center for Labor Studies -- Course Catalog, 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Educational Programs -- "Human Relations and Job Motivation" Paper -- Course Research, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Educational Programs -- Instruction Exercises -- Trivia Questions and Answers, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Publications -- RUB Sheet and S.T.I.R. Report -- Issues and Indexes, undated (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
  - AFL-CIO Food and Beverage Trades Department -- Informational Booklets, Manuals, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - AFL-CIO Food and Beverage Trades Department -- Organizing the 80s, Reducing Delay -- Informational Manual, circa 1981 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
  - International Chemical Workers Union -- 2 Writing Pens, undated (Box 21)
- Series III. Family, 1910-2008; 2.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 oversize flat box.; 4 audiocassettes